<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the reasons which moued Marcus Antonius de Dominis, Archbishop of Spalato or Salonas, primate of Dalmatia and Croatia, to depart from the Romish religion and his countrey. Written by himselfe in Latine, and now for the populare vse translated</title>
            <title>Marcus Antonius de Dominis, Archiepiscopus Spalatensis, suae profectionis consilium exponit. English</title>
            <author>De Dominis, Marco Antonio, 1560-1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20595</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6999</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116248</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851465</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851465</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16739</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20595)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16739)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1685:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the reasons which moued Marcus Antonius de Dominis, Archbishop of Spalato or Salonas, primate of Dalmatia and Croatia, to depart from the Romish religion and his countrey. Written by himselfe in Latine, and now for the populare vse translated</title>
                  <title>Marcus Antonius de Dominis, Archiepiscopus Spalatensis, suae profectionis consilium exponit. English</title>
                  <author>De Dominis, Marco Antonio, 1560-1624.</author>
                  <author>W. S., fl. 1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Andro Hart,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Marcus Antonius de Dominis, Archiepiscopus Spalatensis, suae profectionis consilium exponit.</note>
                  <note>Translater's dedication signed: W.S.</note>
                  <note>Without the Decretum, etc. --STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>De Dominis, Marco Antonio, 1560-1624.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16739:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION <hi>OF THE REASONS</hi> WHICH MOVED MARCVS ANTONIVS DE DOMINIS, ARCHBISHOP <hi>OF</hi> SPALATO OR SALONAS, PRIMATE OF DALMATIA AND CROATIA, to depart from the ROMISH Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion <hi>and his Countrey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WRITTEN BY HIMSELFE IN LATINE, and now for the Populare vſe tranſlated.</p>
            <p>EDINBVRGH, PRINTED BY ANDRO HART, 1617.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:16739:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16739:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16739:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16739:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16739:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16739:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:16739:5"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>TEMPUS</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:16739:5"/>
            <head>THE TRANSLATER imparteth his obſeruation to the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>ECEIVE (CHRISTIAN READER)</hi> a proofe of the force of Trueth, and a praeſage of the ende of that worke God is about to doe in theſe last Ages: A man brought vp in the Learning of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and inchaunted with the Sorceries of <hi>Babel:</hi> without the helpe or counſell of any Proteſtant, by occaſion of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh tyrannie, ſearching the trueth, findeth out their errour in Doctrine, and abuſes in Diſcipline: and conuinced of both, firſt in his minde forſaketh their opinions, and now in his body fleeth from their ſociety. This is not like to the change of <hi>Apollinaris</hi> and <hi>Arrius</hi> of olde, or of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier</hi> in our time, whoſe miſcontented humour, for hopes diſappointed, made them alter their opinion: But more like to that of <hi>Paulus Vergerius,</hi> Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Iuſtinople,</hi> whom vnjuſt ſuspitions at the firſt burdened with a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret fauour of <hi>Lutheraniſme:</hi> for purging whereof he intended a refutation of <hi>Luthers</hi> doctrine: But while he wrangled with the Trueth, to ouer-come it, hee was taken captiue of it: and leauing his Place and Dignities, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered himſelfe at <hi>Tubing</hi> to our Profeſſion.</p>
            <p>The ground of our praeſage is <hi>GODS</hi> Trueth in Times accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherein Prouidence goes on with remarkeable degrees of perſons and places, not without ſome reſpect to the periods of time. Hee rayſed <hi>Wickleff</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:16739:6"/>from their Schooles, <hi>Iohn Huſſe</hi> from their Pulpits, <hi>Martin Luther</hi> from their Cloysters, and nowe <hi>Marke Antonie</hi> from their Arch-epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Chaire. The places haue the like gradation: Great <hi>Britaine</hi> ſeemeth too faire from <hi>Rome,</hi> to waken them by <hi>Wickleffs</hi> crye: Therefore it ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded nearer in <hi>Germanie.</hi> And nowe <hi>Dalmatia</hi> looking ouer the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netian</hi> Gulffe, aſſureth <hi>Italie</hi> that her next Aduertiſer ſhall bee within her bowels. Jt was more than a Poeticall licence to applye <hi>Sybillas</hi> Oracles of CHRIST to <hi>Saloninus</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Pollio,</hi> for keeping in memorie his victorie in taking in <hi>Salonas:</hi> But this our <hi>Saloninus</hi> maketh large reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, and applyeth the Oracles of GOD to the owne purpoſe: As the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie hath gone before, ſo Princes doe follow: The King of <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> with most of the Princes of <hi>Germanie,</hi> ſtand out alreadie againſt <hi>Rome:</hi> The ambiguitie of <hi>France</hi> will reſolue in ende in an open departure: And the temporizing of <hi>Venice</hi> importeth more the want of occaſion, than of will and reſolution. The <hi>Romane</hi> Empire did ſtretch out it ſelfe by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, proceeding from the middes to the extremities, as circles goe out from the Center: And at the extremities againe their ruine began, and went backe to the heart. The fall of their Spirituall Monarchie ſhall keepe the ſame courſe.</p>
            <p>The periods of time haue their owne obſeruation. The <hi>Iewiſh</hi> ſolemnitie of <hi>Iubilee,</hi> not brought in the Church till the thirteenth Age, was then tyed to the Centenarie number: and that their joye hath ſince proued to be like the ſong of the Marmaide before a ſtorme: for ſoone after, <hi>Wickleff</hi> beganne to trouble their mirth: and in the ende of that Age <hi>Iohn Huſſe</hi> made them ſome more buſineſſe: till in the 1415. yeere, the holy Fathers, at <hi>Conſtance</hi> by a Punicke Faith, brought him to the fire. An hundreth yeeres after him <hi>Luther</hi> renewed his ſong with greater boldneſſe, and in the 1517, yeere gaue out his Propoſitions against the Pope: from which time they haue perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded themſelues, and cuen to this daye aſſure their followers, that <hi>Luthers</hi> doctrine can ſtand no longer than an hundreth yeeres. This preſent yeere clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that period: and while they looke for an euaniſhing of that Doctrine, beholde, euen from themſelues it receiueth againe a newe light, anewetesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie. We holde with <hi>Plato</hi> the fatalitie of Periods, but <hi>Pythagoras</hi> num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are too weake a grounde for ſuch a neceſſitie: Or if wee ſhall take anie numbers, it must bee theſe of ſinne; and in ſinne, more the degrees than the numbers. <hi>The Amorites ſinnes muſt come to the height, and the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16739:6"/>Iewes muſt fill their cuppe before their puniſhment.</hi> The Phariſees of our time doe mightily to fill out their meaſure. The pryde and filthineſſe of <hi>Sodome,</hi> the whordomes of <hi>Babell</hi> are now multiplyed exceedingly, and the greateſt ſinne, euen that to death, is become an epidemicke diſeaſe among their Clergie. Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> the 22. can denye the trueth, <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth can ſcoffe at it, <hi>Gardinerus</hi> can confeſſe it at his death, but with this addition, <hi>That it muſt rather ſtill be impugned, than the ſtate of Rome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay:</hi> All their wittes runne vpon this one poinct, but all their meanes turne vpon them: The cruelty of their Inquiſition, The tyranny of their Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Their impudency in falſifying wordes and writs, giue them but a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments aduantage: But euen from theſe ſhall come their rnine. Alye hath no more ſtrength than for the time it is ſpoken, and credulouſly embraced: but the eternall force of Trueth hath more than a momentanie preuailing. What then resteth for them, but that they giue place to the fatality of their estate, ſince they will not giue place to the Trueth. And for vs, while <hi>Rome</hi> is renting in it ſelfe, take heede that we be not diuided. Whoſoeuer now casteth in the apple of ſtrife in the Reformed Church, proueth an enemy to GOD, and an improfitable friend to Antichriſt. Let vs ſtande ſtill, and beholde the worke of the LORD, and bee ſure while wee imagine wee haue left <hi>Babel,</hi> that we haue firſt forſaken <hi>Aegypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W.S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:16739:7"/>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:16739:7"/>
            <head>MARCVS ANTONIVS DE DOMINIS, Arch-Biſhop of SPALATA, expoundeth <hi>the purpoſe and reaſons of</hi> his departing.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Eſt this my departing, ſuddaine and vnexpected of all others, but to my ſelfe, by a long and more than ten yeeres aduiſing reſolued vpon, and by exquiſite deliberation brought to ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſhould cauſe wondring among theſe of our Profeſſion, and ſhould produce ſome badde effectes, through my default, in theſe who are ignorant of the proceeding: I thought it neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie by a timous praeoccupation, to expound the reaſons of this my not-haſtie, but well-aduiſed departing.</p>
            <p>For ſurely I doe foreſee, there ſhall not be lacking many tradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, who according to the cuſtome will take occaſion of this my departing, to reuile, and burden me with calumnies: Which thing I confeſſe before <hi>GOD,</hi> doeth not much trouble mee: For with the Apoſtle PAVL I count little to be judged of men: Let me bee a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16739:8"/>Foole for CHRISTS cauſe: let me bee vyle, buffetted, rayled vpon, perſecuted, blaſphemed, and counted the off-ſcouring of the worlde: yea, and accurſed, ſo that I may ſatisfie the LORD IESVS CHRIST, and profite my brethren in the Miniſterie of CHRIST, I ſhould contemne all theſe thinges. For ont glorie is the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of a good conſcience, that in ſimplicitie of heart, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie of GOD, and not in fleſhly wiſedome: but by the grace of GOD I haue changed my place. It is my parte indeed as the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of GOD, to ſhewe my ſelfe in much patience, in tribulation, in neceſſities, in ſtraites, in laboures, through glorie and ſhame, through infamie and good fame: for I ſeeke not my ſelfe, nor mine owne, but thoſe things which are IESVS CHRISTS, That ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doeth grieue me, if I doe not obviate calumnies, it may eaſily come to paſſe, that in the mindes of the Godly a great fruite of aedification ſhall bee ſtayed, which they might take of my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and that many ignorant of the reaſons of my departing, in place of aedification ſhall vnwittingly offende at me, by vnjuſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies which they will heare. To theſe I will open the reaſons of my departing, and make them manifeſt to all men, that I may profite them.</p>
            <p>That this my change of place is of GOD, and not of man, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may I, neither ought I to call in queſtion: I knowe wee ſhould not eaſily truſt euery Spirit, but ſhould trye them, if they bee of GOD, as we are well admoniſhed by IOHN the beloued Diſciple of CHRIST. Therefore in theſe tryalls, beſide the often acceſſe to the Father of Lightes, which I learued of CHRIST, in theſe ten yeeres before named: it is moſt certaine (as GOD and my Conſcience beareth me recorde) that no mans perſwaſion of whatſoeuer ſort came to my eares: in this purpoſe I had none to ſtirre me vp, none to perſwade me: I had vſe of no mans counſell, nor did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municat it to any creature: Neither yet let any ſuſpect, that I did drawe my reaſons ont of the Bookes (of Proteſtants) which are contrary to the doctrine of ROME: for GOD is my witneſſe, I did vehemently abhorre thoſe Bookes diſcharged by ROMANE Inquiſition: which indeed if any Praelate addicted to the Court of ROME did deteſt, I did it out of meaſure, beeing poſſeſſed from my childhood with
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16739:8"/>fooliſh feares: and ſince now I am not a childe, but neare vnto threeſcore yeeres of age, let any, who liſteth, aſſay whereinto he can perſwade me, without weightie reaſons. I did euer ſway the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations &amp; thoughts of my heart after the rules which the Holie Spirit in Sacred Scripture did praeſcribe to the whole Church: &amp; by whoſe direction the holie and reuerende Fathers euer much eſteemed by the Catholicke Church, did inſtruct the Faithfull: which holie Fathers alſo, beſide the inward motions of the Holie Spirit, were the onlie and chiefe authors of this my purpoſe. Why then ſhould I ſuſpect this worke to bee of an euill ſpirit? From which ſuſpicion that alſo maketh me free, that before GOD, who tryeth the heart and reynes, I know that in my deliberation I did neuer direct my minde to humane or worldlie reſpectes: not vnto Eccleſiaſticall dignities, which might beſeeme mine eſtate, for I was alreadie a Biſhop, and that not of the baſeſt ſort, but the chiefeſt in my natiue Prouince, to wit, <hi>The Archbiſhop of Spalato, the Primate of two Kingdomes, Dalmatia and Croatia,</hi> of as great aeſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in our Churches &amp; Prouinces (I am not aſhamed to confeſſe the trueth) as anie other. And if the dignities of <hi>Rome</hi> had beene pleaſant to me, I had euer an eaſie acceſſe to them. But the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> which I euer diſliked, made me euer to abhorre it: Yet not the leſſe, in great and publicke affaires, the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> did vſe my labours to the Emperour and Archdukes, as is manifeſt by the Popes Brieues, and the Letters of the Emperour and Archdukes, which I yet keepe My well-deſeruing alſo at the hand of the State of <hi>Venice,</hi> my natiue Soueraigne, did procure vnto me their great fauour: whereby I might both hope for, and expect the benefite of a better fortune, if the deſire of greater Grandour had poſſeſſed me. I looked not to worldlie commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which I had in that aboundance as might more than ſuffice a moderate ſpirit, ſuch as I euer had, which I doe aſcribe to the grace of GOD. In this change of my place I doe gladlie embrace the loſſe of all my dignities and riches, becauſe (as I haue ſaid) I ſeeke not mine, but the thinges of IESVS CHRIST: Therefore nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the counſels of men, nor the vndaunted affection, nor worldlie neceſſitie, nor euent: neither anie miſerable accident,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16739:9"/>which vſeth to ranuerſe men, and their eſtate, moued mee to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part: but whence it was, I will ingeniouſly declare, without fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or diſſimulation.</p>
            <p>For the moſt part, from my childhood, I was brought vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> in holy ſtudy, according to the common doctrine of the Schoole-men, and the receiued opinions of the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> for which opinions, proper to <hi>Rome</hi> imprinted and fixed in my mind, more by authoritie than by reaſon: with the miſerable captiuing of my vnderſtanding, I was, for a long ſpace, moſt reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to die: for I counted it execrable about theſe opinions to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the ſmalleſt doubt or ambiguitie of mind or thought, let be of ſpeaches: and being bound vp in this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon reuerence of them, if at any time any thought had crept in againſt them, or my ſtudies had ſuggeſted any doubt, I reſolued to vſe violence againſt mine owne reaſon (as the cuſtome is in matters of Faith) and to turne my minde and thoughts another way, rather than I ſhould admit the leaſt doubt againſt theſe articles of Faith, which I tooke for certaine, and were ſet out to vs by our teachers, to bee moſte cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine. I confeſſe I did feele continually ſome ſparks of the inward Spirit, which neuertheleſſe I reſiſted, yet I could neuer freely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſc, neither free my ſelfe of a great ſuſpicion, which held me in perplexitie, after I had made ſome progreſſe in the ſtudies of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie: Which ſuſpicion was greatly augmented in mee by ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act, ſo rigorous, and inteſtine buſineſſe of <hi>Rome:</hi> whereby I percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued they did moſte narrowly take heede, that no booke, written againſt our doctrine, ſhould bee helde or read by any of vs: for I ſuppoſed, that theſe bookes were juſtly diſcharged the common ſort, leſt the people, who are deſtitute of judgement and diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhold be expoſed by reading of them, to the danger of drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in of Haereſie. But in that they were altogether diſcharged Students, and men of great learning, and well affected to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Religion, I did euer judge (as reaſon will teach euery man) that matter was greatly to bee ſuſpected: eſpecially ſeeing the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> ſuffered vs not to haue any vſe of theſe bookes: euen after wee had compleet our courſe in the ſtudie of Diuinitie, and taken degrees therein: yea, and after our promotion to Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprickes.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16739:9"/>This ſuſpicion did yet more increaſe, where I ſawe our Maſters and Profeſſors in their publicke handling of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies, by word or writ, claime this authoritie to themſelues, to bee truſted in all that they ſayde: that thoſe wordes and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences which they did repeate, were the wordes and ſentences of the aduerſaries: and in the meane time, the hearers were diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, vnder the fearefull paine of Excommunication, to reade the vvritinges of the Aduerſaries: In ryding, ſuppreſſing, and deſtroying vvhereof, they make ſo great buſineſſe, as juſtlie it is to bee ſuſpected, ſome thing lurketh in them which our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is not able to confute.</p>
            <p>From the firſt yeeres wherein I rendered my ſelfe to be a Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie man, I foſtered an in-borne deſire to ſee the vnion of all the Churches of Chriſt: &amp; could neuer patiently thinke vpon the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the <hi>Weſterne</hi> &amp; <hi>Eaſterne</hi> Churches, the <hi>South</hi> &amp; <hi>North</hi> in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of faith. I deſired earneſtly to know the cauſes of ſo many and ſo great <hi>Schiſmes:</hi> and to ſearch, if poſſibly any way could be found out to bind vp again all the Churches of Chriſt in the true &amp; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient vnion. I was alſo tormented with heauy dolour which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued at the diſſentions of Profeſſors of Chriſtian Religion, and the coate of Chriſt ſo miſerably rent aſunder: which dolour and too great heauineſſe did wonderfully afflict mee, and yet more and more vexeth me daylie.</p>
            <p>Thereafter, now ſome twenty yeeres agoe, I was promoued to the gouernement of the Church, and made Biſhop of <hi>Segnat</hi> which thing my Fathers, the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> tooke heauily, becauſe they knew by experience, that I was not ydle, not improfitable for their ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie (but that their account I doe not much regard, for I contemne all humane aeſtimation, vnleſſe it make ſome furtherance to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine obedience) they had found me (I ſay) profitable for them: for in the time of my tryall, when I was but young, they praeferred mee to a publicke profeſſion of HVMANITIE in the Colleges of VERONA. And before I was a Prieſt, they placed mee in the Publicke Chaire, for the profeſſion of the MATHEMATICKES at PADVA, vvith great concourſe of hearers. They made mee Profeſſor of RHETORICKE firſt, and then of the LOGICKE
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16739:10"/>and PHILOSOPHIE, in the Publicke Schooles of BRESCIA, and often on the Feſtuall dayes would needes haue mee making Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in their Churches: They enjoyned mee the diſpatch both of priuate and weightie Affaires: And in all the ſeruices of their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie, they found my diligence: Why then ſhould they not haue taken heauily my promouing to a Biſhoprick? which was vnto me the firſt occaſion to come downe to the earth, from the ſubtill and airie, or improfitable diſputations of the Schoolmen, and to turne my contemplation in wholeſome practiſe of the cure of ſoules, and of the Church. And becauſe I did acknowledge the proper taske of a Biſhop was to preach the Word, I ſet my ſelfe to reade Sermons, and ſuch Bookes as are appointed for Lent: which did ſoone beget in mee a loathing and deteſtation: for I ſawe in them, and that eaſilie, a filthie abuſe of Scripture, while it is throwne to vaine, improfitable, impertinent, yea, and a pernicious ſenſe: I ſaw Examples and Miracles propounded, either falſe and fained, or at leaſt ridiculous, and not worthie of credite: I ſawe the people miſerablie deceiued, and the inuentions of auarice and ambition ſuperſtitiouſlie forced vpon them, vnder colour of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Faith. Theſe thinges I was aſtoniſhed to conſider: and therefore I reſolued to leaue theſe troubled Streames, and to take my ſelfe to the Fountaines of the Fathers: in reading of whoſe works I beganne to delyte, for Sermons and holy Canons, and Church Gouernement.</p>
            <p>From this courſe now and then ſome beames of new light did ſhine vnto me, as yet vnwilling and repining: for on the one part I did obſerue the ſayinges of the Fathers in verie manie thinges, contrarie to the common Doctrine which I had learned in the Schooles: and I did perceiue, that they were either paſſed by in ſilence by my Maſters, or not faithfully alledged, or not ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, or which is worſe, ſiniſtrouſly expounded: On the other part, I did ſee, and that not without great wondring, that the Rule of Church Diſcipline, and Spirituall Gouernement, of our time, was exceeding farre different from the ancient practiſe whereby my forenamed ſuſpicions were greatly augmented: and I percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, a farre off, that we did not faithfully handle the Doctrine and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16739:10"/>Affaires of CHRIST and his Church, but ſluffed our THEOLOGIE rather with the quicke inuentions of humane ſpeculations and Philoſophie, than with the wholſome wordes of holy Scripture, exactly conſidered and expounded, whereof there is a groſſe ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance amongſt vs.</p>
            <p>From a Biſhoprick I was aduanced to an Archbiſhoprick, wherby a new and more vrgent occaſion grew vnto me, to renew my ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and to labour in them more earneſtly: for whereas the troubles of the Suffragane Biſhops of my Prouince, but much more the exceſſiue power of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> encroching vpon my Metropolitane Iuriſdiction, began to injure mee, I proponed to my ſelfe to ſearch out, and throughly to knowe the Root and Fountaine of Church degrees, Iuriſdictions, callings, offices, and dignities; and chiefely of the <hi>Papall</hi> greatneſſe. A little after the State of VENICE was by the Pope put vnder Interdiction: and ſcoffing Pamphlets, ſent dayly from <hi>Rome,</hi> ceaſed not to oppreſſe, vexe, and ſlander all of vs, who were Biſhops of the SEIGNORIE of VENICE, as Beaſtes, Dolts, Ignorantes, and men of euill Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. Whereof, for the better inſtructing our lawfull defences, and for the better knowledge of the quaeſtion debated betwixt the <hi>Venetians</hi> and the Pope, new occaſions were giuen to mee of a new and more earneſt ſtudie. The holy ancient Canons, the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Councels, the Diſcipline of the Fathers, and the ancient cuſtomes of the Church were often and againe turned ouer by me. Whereto ſhall I ſay more? I found aboundantly in theſe only all that I ſought, and a great deale more than I ſought. Then it was eaſie with opened eyes to obſerue that the doctrine of theſe Reformed Churches, which in great numbers <hi>Rome</hi> maketh ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to her ſelfe, and which are bitterly reproued and impugned by our THEOLOGS, did in little, or nothing at all, differ from the true and ancient doctrine of the pure Church. I did alſo perceiue that their doctrine, both at <hi>Rome</hi> and among vs, is abhorred and repelled, rather than lawfully impugned: not for that it is indeede Haereticall and falſe: but only becauſe it is contrary to the corrupt ſenſe and manners of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and to her fleſhly plottes and inuentions, which is nowe turned into a temporall eſtate. I
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16739:11"/>ſaw alſo, &amp; perceiued moſt clearly, that at <hi>Rome,</hi> without any law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ground, yea, by extreame violence, innumerable new articles of faith were daily coined, &amp; forced vpon vs: &amp; that in ſuch things as not only appertaine nothing to diuine faith, but alſo containe in themſelues manifeſt falſehood: Which articles that corrupt Court will neither ſuffer to be diſcuſſed by any, nor be brought in a due conſultation of the Church: but purſueth euen to the death all thoſe who dare whiſper againſt them. They haue now for a long time ſmoothered the ſacred Councels, and ſo haue put out the eyes of the Church of <hi>CHRIST,</hi> that nowe vnhappie ſhee, as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other <hi>Sampſon,</hi> made blinde, and depriued of her owne ſtrength, captiued and made vyle, is able only to groane. It was ſometimes an article of Faith, that the vniuerſall Church, diſperſed through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole worlde, is that Catholicke Church of <hi>CHRIST,</hi> whereunto <hi>CHRIST</hi> himſelfe doeth promiſe his perpetuall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, which PAVL calleth the Pillar and ground of Veritie. But now our <hi>Romanistes</hi> haue drawne this article of Faith in leſſer bounds, That the Catholicke Church now is to be taken for none other than the Court of <hi>Rome:</hi> &amp; it is propounded to be beleeued by a firme Faith, that in it only, yea, &amp; in the <hi>Pope</hi> alone, the whole Spirit of <hi>CHRIST</hi> maketh reſidence: and whatſoeuer of old time hath bene ſaid for the honour of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vniuerſall Church of <hi>CHRIST,</hi> with great injury to the Church, is wholly applyed to the Court of <hi>Rome:</hi> &amp; many things are reduced to the articles of Faith, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we neuer had any inſtitution of <hi>CHRIST:</hi> wherby the ſoules of the Faithfull are miſerably deceiued: and ſo the Blinde with their blind leaders ruſh headlongs in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gulfe of perdition. Theſe things among many other, haue grieued me exceedingly, &amp; doe yet ſtir vp in my ſpirit an incredible dolour.</p>
            <p>But I wil ceaſe now particularly to recount the innumerable no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelties of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and theſe moſte pernicious erroures whereby a Boucherie of ſoules is wrought: the vigour of Church Diſcipline is broken: the propagation and purging of Religion is hindered, and innumerable offences are brought in the Church: the ciuill peace of Chriſtians is troubled, &amp; bloody warres ſtirred vp amongſt them, kingdoms are ouerthrown, &amp; horrible ſchiſmes
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16739:11"/>are made in the Churches, and moſt grieuous calameties do ariſe (which all I haue exactly obſerued) I will ceaſe now (I ſay) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count them, becauſe I haue fully treated of all theſe matters in my large worke, <hi>Of the Eccleſiaſticke Republicke,</hi> which I haue in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe, and ſhall giue to bee Printed in <hi>Germanie,</hi> as firſt commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dioufly occurreth to mee in this my journey: all that worke <hi>Of the Eccleſiasticke Republicke,</hi> I comprehende in ten Bookes: In the firſt whereof I ſearch out the forme of this <hi>Republicke:</hi> and doe deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, that the Church vnder CHRIST appertaineth to a moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Monarchie: and that not the leſſe the Miniſters of CHRIST on earth, by CHRISTS own inſtitution, are moſt farre from an earthly Monarchie, &amp; do gouerne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church with an <hi>Ariſtocratie</hi> or choiſe gouernment: not without ſome mixture of a <hi>democratie</hi> or popular gouernment: and conſequently I ſhew that the <hi>Primacie</hi> of <hi>Peter</hi> is contrary to the <hi>Euangel</hi> &amp; inſtitution of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> In the ſecond booke I conſider the gouerners &amp; Miniſters of the <hi>Eccleſiaſticke Republick,</hi> who they are, &amp; what ſucceſſion can be giuen to the holy <hi>Apoſtles:</hi> what is the inſtitution of <hi>Biſhops:</hi> wherein they differ from <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters:</hi> who are the inferiour Miniſters, and what force holie Order haue in this <hi>Republicke.</hi> In the thirde I doe expound what is the Hierarchie to bee found among the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and Gouernoures of this <hi>Republick:</hi> and I do teach, that there is no praeheminence nor ſubjection among <hi>Biſhops,</hi> by diuine right, but that degrees of pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces among them are diſtinguiſhed by the conſtitutions of the Church only. And conſequently I doe treat of the <hi>Election, Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, Conſecration</hi> or <hi>Ordination</hi> of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and of the power of <hi>Metropolitanes, Primates,</hi> and <hi>Patriarches.</hi> In the fourth I exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Priuiledges of the Church of ROME: and doe proue, that neither in her ſelfe, nor in her Biſhop nor Clergie, ſhee hath anie praeheminence giuen her of <hi>CHRIST</hi> aboue other Churches: but if anie ſhee hath had, or nowe hath, ſhee hath taken it from the helpes and furtherances of men. In the fifth I doe vndertake to ſearch out the proper power of the CHVRCH: and doe prooue, that it is meerelie Spirituall: and ſo I remooue, farre from the CHVRCH, all (Earthlie) IVRISDICTION: And then conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16739:12"/>I diſpute of the force and operation of Sacramentes, and of Eccleſiaſticall Cenſures. In the ſixth I compare the power of the Laitie, and of the Church; that the difference betwixt the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticke and Temporall Republicke may appeare; and I doe ſhewe that Chriſtian temporall Princes may doe many thinges in the Church: but the Church in temporall thinges, and eſpecially towards Kings, may doe nothing at all. I treat alſo of the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Kingdome of CHRIST, of the power of the Laitie whence it is, and of how large extent: of the Immunities of the Church and Church-men: of Inueſtitures, of the Monarchie of SICILL, and ſuch like. In the ſeuenth I conſider the inward direction of the Eccleſiaſticke Republicke, which is by faith: and I inquire for the true rule of faith: and ſo I diſpute of the Word of GOD, of the authoritie of the Church, and of the Pope ouer it: of Councels, of Haereſie, of Schiſme, and ſuch like. In the eight I conſider the externall gouernement of the Church, by Lawes, Canons, and Iudicatories. Thereafter I diſcuſſe howe farre Canons doe obliſh: of diſpenſations, of commandes, enjoyning faſting, prayer, and ſuch like. In the ninth I come to the temporall goods of the Church, and I expound at length how ſparing the ſuſtentation of the Miniſters ſhould bee: whence it ſhould bee taken: and howe Church goods ſhould be guided. I treat alſo of Tithes, of Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, of dominion ouer Church-goods: of the vſe and abuſe of Church-rents: of Penſions, of Commendas, and Teſtaments of the Clergie. In the tenth and laſt I vndertake to expound the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Church, that wee may ſee what way this Republicke is free. And conſequently I treat of Priuiledges, and perſons priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged: of the abuſe of priuiledges: of exemptions, and perſons exempted: of the ſubjection of Moncks, and ſuch like. This was the fruit of my painfull ſtudies: for while vpon the occaſions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore named I did griedily reade holy Scripture, the Orthodox Fathers, the holy Canons, and Volumes of Councels, mine eyes being opened, and I inflamed with a zeale to explaine the trueth to others, and to my ſelfe, I could not but write thoſe thinges I obſerued: and this my much writing hath begotten this worke, the ſumme whereof I haue rehearſed. I ſaw therefore plainly, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16739:12"/>did perceiue, that in our Churches wee had gone farre aſtray from the right path both in Doctrine and Diſcipline.</p>
            <p>What then ſhould I doe more in the mids of a wicked &amp; froward nation? If (as reaſon craueth) I would haue gouerned mine owne Church according to the ancient diſcipline of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Catholick Church, and propone true and Catholick doctrine, I ſhould by that meanes haſten vpon mine head great ſtormes &amp; horrible tempeſts fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Rome:</hi> for eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> already at <hi>Rome</hi> great hatred was hatched &amp; foſtered againſt mee, becauſe they had vnder-ſmelled my labours in writing againſt their opinions: for which I was often admoniſhed &amp; rebuked by the Popes <hi>Nuncio,</hi> lying at <hi>Venice:</hi> it was therfore much better to take the wings of a <hi>doue,</hi> &amp; to withdraw my ſelfe, &amp; fly away to the wildernes, where I might wait vpon him who will deliuer me from the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ſpirit, &amp; from the tempeſt: rather than remaining among the blind, willingly blinding my ſelfe, I ſhould leade the blind to perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. What are the Biſhops vnder the <hi>Romane</hi> Popedome? In tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall things indeed, where the benefices are fat, they ſhine in wordly dignitie, they are great, &amp; conſpicuous, &amp; Princes: but Biſhops they are not, but by aequiuocation: all their Biſhoply adminiſtration is periſhed: for the gouernment of all Churches is drawn to <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Biſhops themſelues are ſcarſely Vicars and ſeruants to the <hi>Lord Pope:</hi> they are vile, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temptible, oppreſſed, &amp; troden vnder foot mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably: ſubjected not to the <hi>Pope</hi> only, but to Cardinals &amp; to ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregations as are inſtitute at <hi>Rome</hi> againſt them: Legates from his <hi>Holines</hi> ſide, <hi>Apoſtolick Nunces, Inquiſitors, Viſitors,</hi> &amp; in end to innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable Orders of Regulars, and their brethren, who now by their Apoſtolicke priuiledges are uot onely aequalled to Biſhops, but alſo ouermatcheth them, &amp; ſtayeth their proceedinges in their gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſwallowing vp their power. The Church vnder the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is no more a Church, but a certaine humane Commonwealth, all of it vnder the <hi>Popes</hi> temporall Monarchie: It is a Vineyard only to make <hi>Noe</hi> drunke: it is a Flock, which the Shepheards do ſheare and clip euen to the blood: yea, to excoriate and flaye them. Why then ſhould I not flee, leſt I ſhould ſee theſe euils any longer, &amp; leſt I ſhould be a fellow-worker of ſuch thinges, &amp; a partaker with them. CHRIST hath ſet mee as a dogge among his flocke: I ſhould not bee dumbe anie longer, as nowe all the other Biſhops vnder the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16739:13"/>
               <hi>Romane</hi> pope are dumb dogs: who on the one part allured with large <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pes, and on the other terrified with great feare, are altogether ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent: and chooſe by baſe flattery to haſten to perdition with their Chiftane. And becauſe (according to the Prouerbe) <hi>Flattery begetteth friends, and trueth begetteth hatred:</hi> ſeeing I neither could, nor ought to deſert the trueth, I behoued of neceſſitie to flee noiſome hatred, and poyſon, and daggers, the ordinary effects of hatred among vs: for in theſe our times matters are come to this poinct, that at <hi>Rome,</hi> or elſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where by commiſſion from <hi>Rome,</hi> the defence of Controuerſies of Religion is not committed to <hi>Theologs</hi> or Councels, but to Tortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, Burrios, Cut-throates, and bloodie Murtherers.</p>
            <p>And albeit all theſe things did euer and earneſtly perſwade me to flee yet I doe confeſſe I fonnd the handmaide <hi>Agar,</hi> with her childe <hi>Jſmael,</hi> for a long time troubleſom to me: I mean I heard my fleſh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belling againſt my ſpirit, and reaſoning after this manner: And whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I pray thee, wilt thou goe? Thou art come to great dignities, &amp; wealth, vnder the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> with hope alſo to attaine further. Theſe things thou doeſt poſſeſſe: theſe are certain, but thou knoweſt not what ſhall befall thee in other places. Shall it bee euen ſo, that thou wilt leaue thy Countrey, &amp; Conſignes, &amp; Alliance, &amp; friends, neuer any more to ſee them againe? Wherfore makeſt thou thy ſelfe wiſer than innumerable other Biſhops, who comporteth vvith all things, tolerateh &amp; excuſeth them? why wilt not thou in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner comport with, tolerate &amp; excuſe them? Art thou only the wiſe man among ſuch an innumerable multitude? Are all the reſt foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh? Doeſt thou not know, that immediatly after thy departing, firſt at <hi>Rome,</hi> and then euery where, thou ſhalt bee burdened with great reproaches, and noted with the infamous name of an Haereticke? Theſe and more ſuch like ſpeaches my fleſhly <hi>Agar</hi> did often whiſper in mine eares, not without a great combate betwixt her &amp; mine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ſpirit, and my Conſcience nowe already ouercome with the trueth: But that diuine Spirit, with a more vehement force, ſuffered me not any longer to make delayes, but with an effectuall voyce he called me to himſelfe, as he did <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſaying <hi>Come out of thy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and from thy kinred, and from thy Fathers houſe, and come vnto the Land which I will ſhew vnto thee.</hi> And he forced mee to put in execution that notable ſaying of the wiſe men, FOLLOW GOD: euen as bleſſed
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16739:13"/>
               <hi>Abraham</hi> indeed obeyed it, according to the conſideration of holie <hi>Ambroſe (de Abraham. lib. 1. cap. 2.)</hi> Which fact of the holy Patriarch after a wonderfull ſort, augmented both my courage and ſtrength, while I perceiued, that GOD did firſt rewarde his ready obedience, by keeping diſgrace and infamie farre from him: for hee praeſerued the chaſtity of his beautiful wife <hi>Sara,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was in liazard by a licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Tyrant. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> alſo did much comfort mee in this caſe, while he ſaith, Becauſe <hi>Abraham</hi> contemned all things for GODS calling, therfore he receiueth al things again abundantly multiplied: &amp; firſt of all hee gaue him the ſafety of <hi>Saras</hi> chaſtity, which hee knew was deare to the husband. That ſame holy Father addeth moreouer, Whoſoeuer followeth the LORD is euer in ſurety: &amp; therefore (ſaith he) we ſhould not bee called backe from the obedience of heauenlie commandements, neither for reſpect to our countrey, or parents, or children, or wife, becauſe GOD giueth all theſe gifts to vs, &amp; is able to preſerue them all. Theſe things giue mee full aſſurance, that for this my following of his calling, though it bee ſomewhat too late, GOD will giue me this remuneration, euen the praeſeruation of my fame and aeſtimation: that of whatſoeuer account it be, it ſhall ſuffer no diſgrace amongſt <hi>Barbarians,</hi> but ſhall be kept found and vndefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for the aedification of ſome, and auoyding of offences. Beeing therefore encouraged with this confidence, and moued with this holy calling and admoniſhed by theſe dangers, I haue moſt cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully vndertaken this my flight.</p>
            <p>But yet the loue of CHRIST conſtraineth me, for I might be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of a vile &amp; baſe ſpirit, if laying aſide all lawfull ſtriuing, I ſhould rot in ſluggiſh idleneſſe in ſome corner, and ſo flee for mine owne eaſe. The cauſe of CHRIST is in hand, which calleth me to it ſelfe, &amp; I heare that voyce continually thundering in mine eares [CRYE] and admoniſhing mee to goe vp to ſome high mountaine, to the ende that my voyce, joyned with their voyce, who haue not bowed their knee to <hi>Baal,</hi> may bee better heard in preaching the Goſpel to <hi>Sion.</hi> That voyce now I follow, and I goe into ſome mountain, where the Catholick Church hath lifted vp her head in a free profeſſion, from whence, according to the obliſhment of my calling, ſo farre as in me lieth, I may proclaime the trueth to the worlde: and may open and ſhew the wayes for taking away all diuiſions, and binding vp again
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16739:14"/>of peace in the Church. The Church ſhall ſhortly heare my cries, &amp; I will ſpeake to the heart of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and call vnto her: For I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in any caſe bee lacking to my calling, becauſe I am a Biſhop in the Church of CHRIST. &amp; to euery Biſhop his own particular Church is ſo committed, that hee muſt in the meane time vnderſtand, where there is any neceſſity of his helpe, the vniuerſall Church is recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to him by IESVS CHRIST. To all of vs who are Biſhops the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> hath ſaid, <hi>Take heed to your ſelues, &amp; to the whole flocke ouer which the Spirit of God hath made you ouer-ſieers, to rule the Church of God, which he hath purchaſed with his own blood.</hi> Theſe words alſo are giuen out in the name of <hi>Eleutherius</hi> an ancient Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> writing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other Biſhops, <hi>For this cauſe Chriſt hath committed vnto you the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Church, that ye labour for all men: and neglect not to helpe all, according to neceſſity. Cyprian</hi> alſo affirmeth <hi>(epiſt. 13. lib. 3)</hi> that joyntly with <hi>Stepha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> he did hold the leuell of gouerning the Church. And then he addeth, <hi>The body of the Prieſthood is exceeding large, and is coupled together with the glew of mutuall concord, and the band of vnity: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if any of our fellowſhip ſhall praſume to forge an haereſie, or to rent &amp; deſtroy the Church of Chriſt, let all the reſt make conuenient helpe.</hi> And that ſame <hi>Cyprian</hi> in very deede often helped troubled Churches: euen ſuch as were without the bounds of <hi>Africke:</hi> yea and the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe. So <hi>Polycarpus, Irenaeus, Oſius</hi> of <hi>Corduba, Athanaſius, Baſilius,</hi> the two <hi>Euſebii,</hi> one of <hi>Samoſata,</hi> &amp; the other of <hi>Vercels, Lucifer</hi> of <hi>Calarie, Hilarie</hi> of <hi>Poitiers, Theophilus</hi> and <hi>Cyrillus</hi> of <hi>Alexandria, Aurelius</hi> of <hi>Carthage,</hi> and many other Biſhops, did painfully labour, by vertue of their Epiſcopall office, to helpe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> necſſities of the vniuerſal Church: and leauing, for a ſpace, their own Churches, well appointed, reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending them to the ouerſight of others, they went vnto other af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted &amp; troubled Churches. Therefore it is moſt proper to my cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, &amp; not without the compaſſe of it, with all my might, as <hi>Cyprian</hi> exhorteth, to helpe the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> which factionouſly maketh a Sect, and deuiding it ſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Church, renteth &amp; deſtroyeth the Church of CHRIST: and yet mine helpe muſt not be by approching to it, becauſe that is not ſure: but by a bodily departing from it. I would indeed moſt gladly haue retained mine own Church of <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> as <hi>Oſius, Baſilius,</hi> the two <hi>Euſebii, Hilarius,</hi> &amp; others aboue named, retained their own Churches, &amp; returned vnto them after they had
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16739:14"/>ended the publicke buſineſſe of the vniuerſall Church. But becauſe that my Church, with many others, groaneth vnder the tyrannie of the <hi>Pope,</hi> who hateth &amp; abhorreth Reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; and by all his power and the forces of his adhaerent Princes, maketh impediment to it: And hauing power of life &amp; death ouer theſe who ſuit &amp; vrge refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, ſuffereth none of them aliue. Therefore, I could not chooſe, but leaue my Church, that I my ſelfe, hauing caſt off theſe bands, &amp; ſet at liberty, might be the more ready to proclaime the trueth, and with greater ſafety might deplore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſolation of the holy Church, which ſhe ſuffereth of the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>True it is, the majeſty of an earthly king is dreadfull, <hi>becauſe</hi> (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith) <hi>he is next vnto God, &amp; leſſer than God only: aboue whom</hi> (as <hi>Optatus Milevitanus</hi> ſaith) <hi>there is none ſaue God alone.</hi> Therefore when k. <hi>Dauid</hi> was to be reproued for his adultery &amp; murther, neither the high <hi>Prieſt,</hi> nor any other of the <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> nor any <hi>Leuit,</hi> or friend or familiar durſt praeſume to take that charge vpon him: but God vſed his own proper &amp; peculiar meſſenger, &amp; appointed the <hi>Prophet Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> to rebuke him. But there is not now ſuch neceſſity: neither need we expect, that God will raiſe vp extraordinary <hi>Prophets,</hi> &amp; appoint peculiar meſſengers to deal with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> who is now trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, ſcandalizing, ſpoyling, &amp; oppreſſing the whole Church. The majeſty of our <hi>Rom. Pope</hi> is not ſo great as to affray vs, that his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall &amp; hauty majeſty is fained, vſurped, &amp; is none at all, he is but our <hi>Brother</hi> &amp; <hi>Collegue,</hi> &amp; a <hi>Biſhop</hi> with vs, &amp; a <hi>Fellow-ſeruant</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> work: and a brother who is holpen of a brother, is as a fenced city, as <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſaith in the <hi>Prouerbs.</hi> Wherfore then doe we ſnort? wherfore doe we ſleep? a <hi>Brother</hi> periſheth, &amp; draweth the Churches away with him to perdition, &amp; we his <hi>Brethren</hi> neglect the danger &amp; doe not occur. Let all be ſilent, let all be quiet, &amp; contemn as they will, yet I y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt <hi>Whelpe</hi> among them all, with ſuch barking as I can, ſhall wake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe great <hi>maſtius,</hi> who are aſleep, &amp; made drowſie by a wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful policy of the <hi>Popedome:</hi> that according to their charge they may hold back the <hi>Wolues,</hi> &amp; ſaue the flock of Ieſus Chriſt. I ſhall not vſe mine own voyce, but the voyce of God, in wakening the good <hi>Dogs:</hi> and I ſhall double vpon them the Cry of holy Fathers, &amp; Councels, &amp; holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church. As for theſe ten Bookes, <hi>Of the Eccleſiaſtick Republick,</hi> which I am ſhortly to put to light, I ſhall ſpecially endeuour, that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16739:15"/>the errours of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> may be detected, the trueth and wholſomnes of the Catholick doctrine &amp; diſcipline may be opened, &amp; theſe many (reformed) Churches, which by our <hi>Romane</hi> Church are proudly caſten off &amp; diuorced, may be retained in a Catholik ſenſe, and that the way of vnion of all the Churches, if not clearly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat, may be at leaſt pointed out: if by any means we can be broght to that eſtate, all of vs to thinke one thing, &amp; to ſay one thing: that <hi>Schiſmes</hi> may be remedied, and all occaſions taken away from Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Princes, of plotting the ouerthrow one of another, &amp; of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling the common peace of Chriſtian people, with vntimous &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly warres, &amp; that vnder the praetence of Faith &amp; Religion: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that all their forces may be ſo directed, as the Catholik Church of Chriſt, groaning vnder the tyrannie of thoſe who are <hi>Infideles</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, may be reſtored to her ancient libertie.</p>
            <p>This my departing from my Countrey, or rather my going out &amp; flight from <hi>Babel,</hi> I will that it want all ſuſpicion of <hi>Schiſme:</hi> for I flee from errours, I flee from abuſes, &amp; that leſt I be partaker of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels</hi> ſinnes, and receiue of her plagues: yet will I neuer ſeuer my ſelfe from the loue which I owe to the holy Catholick Church, and to all and euery one who communicate with her: but ſo far as in me lieth, I ſhall euer bee ready to communicate with them all, ſo long as wee agree in the eſſentiall articles of our Faith, and the Creedes of the ancient Church of Chriſt, if in the meane time we dereſt &amp; abhorre all new articles of Faith, which are contrary to holy Scripture, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the forenamed Creedes: and that we admit not, in anie caſe, articles indifferent in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, as articles of Faith, which haue neuer bene ſufficiently diſcuſſed, eſtabliſhed and determined by the Church, except firſt they be fully determined, or bee ſhowne to haue bene determined of before: neither yet that we condemne thoſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles as haereticall, vnleſſe we haue ſufficient notice that they haue bene condemned by the Church. In things therefore indifferent, let liberty of opinion and action be permitted to euery Church: and let euery of them abound in their own judgement, vntill the Church it ſelfe, inſtructed &amp; gouerned by the Spirit of Chriſt, ſhall put an ende to controuerſies, and ſeuer the <hi>Chaffe</hi> from the true <hi>Corne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the meane time, let vs remember that notable ſaying of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie <hi>Cyprian,</hi> which hee vſed in the Councill of <hi>Carthage, Wee judge no
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16739:15"/>man</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>neither debar we any man from the Communion, albeit he haue an opinion diuerſe from vs: for none of vs all hath made himſelfe Biſhop of Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, or compelleth his collegues, by a tyrannicall force, to the neceſſitie of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience: becauſe euery Biſhop, according to liberty and power, hath his own arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment: as though hee might not bee judged by others, neither hee himſelfe may judge another: but let vs all await vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the judgement of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, who one, and alone, hath power to prafer vs to the gouernment of his Church, and to take an account of all our proceedings.</hi> At that time <hi>Cyprian</hi> diſaſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp; almoſt from the vniuerſal Church, about the Baptiſme of Haeretickes: and being confirmed in his own opinion, hee judged <hi>Stephanus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> who mightily reſiſted him therein, and all other, to bee in a manifeſt errour: yet hee neuer ſuffered the band of vnion &amp; Eccleſiaſtick Charity betwixt them, to be broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, leſt a <hi>Schiſme,</hi> the moſt noyſome peſt of the Church, ſhould atiſe among them. And in this, <hi>Cypr.</hi> to his great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation, did ouercome the not-all-wiſe-diſcrete zeale of <hi>Stephanus:</hi> for while as <hi>Steph.</hi> by his exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munications, did ruſh headlongs to the inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience of a <hi>Schiſme, Cyprian</hi> by his patience and charity, &amp; excellent wiſdome, eſchewed a ſeparation. Therfore S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> did ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and propounded his actions as a rule and examplar of Imitation to all the Churches.</p>
            <p>And among other thinges which <hi>Auguſtine</hi> conſidereth of this proceeding &amp; ſtrife betwixt <hi>Cyprian</hi> &amp; <hi>Stephanus,</hi> hee ſaith (in his fifth booke againſt the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> chap. 25.) <hi>Yet the peace of Chriſt did ſo prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile in their hearts, that in ſuch a quaeſtion no Schiſme did ariſe betwixt them:</hi> for <hi>Cyprian</hi> had ſurely concluded with himſelfe, that <hi>Steph.</hi> did groſly erre, while he receiued poenitent Haereticks, returning to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church, without rebaptizing: yet hee chooſed to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate not only with <hi>Stephanus</hi> himſelfe, who thought and did contrary to him: but alſo with thoſe whom he judged to be altogether vncleane: and that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe <hi>Steph.</hi> had receiued them to the Communion, rather than to rent the Church with a <hi>Schiſme.</hi> And this example <hi>Auguſtine</hi> propoundeth to the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> and vs all, to be followed.</p>
            <p>Therefore, moſt holy Father, &amp; you Fathers &amp; Brethren, and holy Collegues, let vs imitate <hi>Cyprian,</hi> &amp; follow the counſell of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> that aboue all things, <hi>Schiſmes</hi> be remoued: for (as <hi>Auguſt.</hi> obſerueth) <hi>Cyprian</hi> repleniſhed, with the bowels of charity aeſtimed, that euen
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16739:16"/>they who haue diuerſe opinions, ſhould abide in vnitie. Let vs alſo among vs haue diuerſe opinions, of thinges not as yet determined, till they be fully determined: And in the meane time let vs abide in vnity: for albeit that you thinke otherwiſe, yet (as th'Apoſtle admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth) God will reueale that to you. Make not greater diuiſions than are already. Take heed alſo that with <hi>Stephanus</hi> ye break not the band of charity, by vntimous excommunications, leſt by ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, that great ill of diuiſion ariſe, which <hi>Auguſt.</hi> did fore-eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chew: Reſtore peace and charity to all the Churches of <hi>CHRIST,</hi> who according to the Tenor of the ancient Creedes doe profeſſe <hi>IES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> and bee aſſured of this, that <hi>Schiſme</hi> in the Church is a farre more grieuous euill than Haereſie. Haue your <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> ready for all, without praejudice of the liberty of opinions: remouing in the meane time all falſehoods in doctrine. Leaue the examinations of the Trueth to thoſe lawfull &amp; accuſtomed formes of the holy Church: for ſo I hope, through the aſſiſting grace of <hi>CHRIST,</hi> who vſeth not to denie himſelfe to them who ſeeke him ſincerely, that full peace and concord, and a neceſſary vnion of the holy Churches ſhall follow, that we all think one thing, &amp; abide all in one rule. Let vt not ſtirre vp amongſt vs the fire of hatred and ſecret grudges, but of Religion and Catholicke inſtruction. Let the Word of <hi>GOD</hi> bee a Lanterne to our feete, and let vs followe the foot-ſteps of our holy Anceſtors, who haue beene excellent Lightes in the Church of <hi>CHRIST.</hi> Let vs breake aſunder, without pertina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, the darkneſſe of errour and falſehood, by the light of the trueth of the Goſpel: and let vs depart farre from Nouelties, which haue almoſt quite exſtinguiſhed the Doctrine and Diſcipline of the holie Church: that the Church of <hi>CHRIST</hi> on earth may bee one coupled together with the glew of concorde: wherein to let vs all with one ſpirit and one mouth prayſe our <hi>GOD,</hi> and the Father of our <hi>LORD IES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> AMEN,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Giuen at</hi> VENICE, <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> xv, <hi>of September.</hi> ANNO 1616.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16739:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16739:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16739:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16739:18"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16739:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
